<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons The Christians comfort in his crosses, conducting him in the tempests of tribulation, to the happie hauen of heauenly tranquillitie. And the iudges, and iuries instruction. By William Est, Maister of Art, and preacher of Gods word.</title>
            <author>Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00409</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118617</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853824</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853824</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19222</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00409)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19222)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 578:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons The Christians comfort in his crosses, conducting him in the tempests of tribulation, to the happie hauen of heauenly tranquillitie. And the iudges, and iuries instruction. By William Est, Maister of Art, and preacher of Gods word.</title>
                  <author>Est, William, 1546 or 7-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 42, [2]; [6], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho: Creede, for Arthur Iohnson, dwelling at the signe of the white Horse in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The iudges and iuries instruction" has separate dated title page; register and pagination continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:1"/>
                  <p>TWO SERMONS.</p>
                  <p>THE CHRISTIANS COMFORT IN HIS CROSSES, CONDVCTING him in the tempeſts of tribulation, to the happie hauen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly tranquillitie.</p>
                  <p>AND THE IVDGES, AND IVRIES INSTRVCTION.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>William Eſt,</hi> Maiſter of Art, and Preacher of Gods word.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom: 8.18.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> count that the afflictions of this preſent time are not worthie of the glorie which ſhall be ſhewed vnto vs.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>AT LONDON. Printed by <hi>Tho: Creede,</hi> for <hi>Arthur Iohnſon,</hi> Dwelling at the ſigne of the white Horſe in Pauls Church-yard. 1614.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:2"/>
                  <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Haue here (Gentle Reader) exhibited to thy viewe, the chiefeſt Obſeruations and Doctrines of the beſt Learned, and moſt approoued wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Latine tongue, vpon this Texte, both ancient and moderne, beſides very many of mine owne, neuer before publiſhed. Wherein (as the ſearcher of hearts knoweth) I haue not affected the popular applauſe of the worlde, which I holde but the wauering winde of mens mouthes, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out the vaine blaſtes of that many-headed Monſter, whoſe minde is euer mutable,<note place="margin">Vulgus belluo mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitum.</note> which I haue euer reputed no better then a verball ſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. I can hardly thinke him to bee a good man of whom all men ſpeake well; for this plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, that he can apply himſelfe to the perſon, how odious ſoeuer hee be: to the time, how wicked ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be: to the place, how vnhoneſt ſoeuer it be. But the glory of God I haue euer prefixed, as the onely ſcope and marke whereunto all my labours doe ayme: &amp; the loue of Sion enforceth me by all meanes to ſeeke to further the courſe of godlines.
<pb facs="tcp:19222:3"/> Wherefore Chriſtian Reader, I doe requeſt thee iudicially to iudge, Chriſtianly to Cenſure, and charitably correct, whatſoeuer hath paſſed my hands, <hi>pingui craſſa<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Minerua,</hi> through ſome ouerſight. Awd aboue all, aſſiſt me with thy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Almightie God, that theſe, and all other my labours, may bee as I haue intended, to the glorie of God, and Edification of his Church. As for the Cynick ſtraines of <hi>Criticall Zoilus,</hi> or blacke-mouthed <hi>Momus,</hi> which wanting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes, thinke to vindicate vnto themſelues an opinion of learning among the ſimple, by cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; carping at the honeſt enterpriſes of others, which will ſooner find two faults in another, then amend one in themſelues. Let ſuch knowe, that I diſdaine to giue them any other anſwere, then <hi>Martiall</hi> the Poet (though of farre greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert) did once to one of that curſed crue:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Mart. lib. 9. Epigr. 99.</note>
                           <hi>Rumpitur inuidia, quod amamur,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>quod<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> probamur,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Rumpatur quiſquis, Rumpitur inuidia.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>With Enuie ſome in ſunder breake,</l>
                        <l>to ſee me loued well:</l>
                        <l>Aſunder let him breake,</l>
                        <l>whoſe gall with Enuie ſo doth ſwell.</l>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>And thus I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit my good meaning to the iudgement of the honeſt, who are wont to take good meaning euer in the better part.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine in the Lord. <hi>W.</hi> Eſt.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:3"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, WILLIAM <hi>EARLE OF BATH, HIS</hi> MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Chiefe Lieutenant in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Deuon</hi> and <hi>Cornwall:</hi> all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in this life, and eternall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe in the life to come.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y continuall imployme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts (Right Honourable) in the function of my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, might put a ſtrong <hi>Remora</hi> to my pen, to ſtay me from farther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraying my vnskilfulnes in writing, had not my intire loue to <hi>Sion</hi> ouerſwayed all difficulties, and vanquiſhed all laboures and impediments. Theſe <hi>2. Sermons</hi> I preached before a great and iuditious <hi>Auditorie.</hi> The one, which I haue intituled; <hi>The Iudges and Iuries In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> by commaund of authoritie, long ſince before the <hi>Iudges,</hi> at the <hi>Aſſiſes</hi> at <hi>Lanceſton,</hi> when that worſhipfull <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb facs="tcp:19222:4"/> Sir Bernard Greynuile,</hi> my good <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron,</hi> was <hi>Shieriffe</hi> of <hi>Cornwall.</hi> The other <hi>(The Chriſtians Comfort)</hi> is more recent: And chancing of late vpon certayne Copies and notes, pretended to bee taken from my mouth, as I then deliuered them, I found ſome maymed and defectiue, ſome patched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in an indigeſted maner, and other vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly falſe and miſtaken; which hath enforced me (and the rather through the importunitie of ſome of my beſt friends) to ſearch out the originall, and to diſrobe this forlorne of-ſpring of his counterfeite colours, and patched coate; and to put vpon him his owne ſuite, though in the playneſt faſhion, without any curious dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king or trimming. Which when I had effected (I confeſſe) my ambiguous thoughts were toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed too and fro for a while, in a deepe and doubtfull <hi>dilemma</hi> (euery way conuincing) vnder whoſe <hi>Pratrocinie</hi> I might ſend forth this my poore abortiue <hi>Orphane</hi> abroad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world: But at length my diſtracted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution preſumed to alight vpon your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Honourable name, to ſeeke ſhelter againſt enuie and detracting tongues, being imboldned by the generall report, and my owne tryall of your <hi>Honours heroicall</hi> propenſion, and noble diſpoſition to pietie, learning, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion:
<pb facs="tcp:19222:4"/> Wherewith, and with all other orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of vertues fit for ſuch a <hi>Perſonage,</hi> God hath ſo plentifully endowed you, that it were better in ſilence to paſſe that ouer, which I cannot ſufficiently commend, then by taking vpon mee to illuſtrate your deſerued prayſes: I might (perchance) ſeeme to derogate from the worth thereof, by ſpeaking too little (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being ſo perſpicuous and eminent to the eyes of all men) that I might iuſtlie be taxed with this prouerbe; <hi>Solem lucerna oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere.</hi> And it might be ſayd vnto me, as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talcides</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Antalci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> ſayd to an <hi>Oratour,</hi> who had made a long ſpeech in the praiſe of <hi>Hercules; Quis vnquam ſanus eum vituperauit? What man well in his wits euer diſpray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him?</hi> The <hi>ſearcher of hearts</hi> knoweth I ſpeake without flatterie, which I euer dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted as a <hi>verball ſimonie.</hi> Theſe my poore labours I commend vnto your <hi>Honourable</hi> protection: poore (I confeſſe) if you looke into the manner of handling of it, and the ſubſtance of the gifte. But my deſire and hope is, that it ſhall find that acceptance with your <hi>Honor,</hi> that <hi>Sinetas</hi> handfull of water did with the great <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Artax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erxes.</note> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie receiued it with alacritie of minde, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renitie of countenance, eſtimating the wiking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19222:5"/> of the Giuer, before the value of the gift, being the beſt that the poore man had to offer. And as <hi>Plinie</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plinie.</note> ſaith; The poore people that had no Frankencenſe did offer Milke, and they that wanted Milke, did offer Salt vnto their gods, with good acceptance; according to the prouerbe; <hi>Mola ſalſa litant qui non habent thura.</hi> The God of all mercy, powre downe the riches of his mercies vpon your <hi>Honour,</hi> and multiply your daies vpon earth, to the good of the Church &amp; Common-wealth, that you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y long continue a ſtaie and comfort to theſe Weſterne parts, and after the race of this mortall life being runne, graunt you the eternall bleſſedneſſe of his heauenlie King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips in all dutie deuoted, WILLIAM EST.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19222:5"/>
                  <head>THE FIRST SERMON.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Mat. 8. verſ. 23.24.25.26.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>23.</hi>
                           </bibl> And when he was entred into the ſhip his Diſciples followed him.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>24.</hi>
                           </bibl> And behold there aroſe a great tempeſt in the ſea, ſo that the ſhip was couered with waues: but he was a ſleepe.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>25.</hi>
                           </bibl> Then his Diſciples came, and awooke him, ſaying; Maiſter, ſaue vs: we periſh.</p>
                        <p>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>26.</hi>
                           </bibl> And he ſaid vnto them, why are ye feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ô ye of little faith? then he aroſe, and rebuked the windes and the ſea: and ſo there was a great calme.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THis part of ſcripture, is hiſtoricall, and ſheweth the miraculous cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of an horrible tempeſt, Chriſt and his Diſciples being in the ſhip, and therefore pertaineth <hi>ad genus demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19222:6"/>
                  <p>In the diſcription of this miracle.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Certaine circumſtances are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</item>
                     <item>2. The te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt it ſelfe is deſcribed.</item>
                     <item>3. The calming of the tempeſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> noted.</item>
                     <item>4. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t effects are added.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the firſt part. <hi>Mar:</hi> 4.</note>Firſt the circumſtances are ſet downe, whereof the 1. is <hi>ab adiuncto tempore,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the time when it happened, <hi>when he was entered into the ſhip,</hi> which was about the <hi>euening:</hi> the 2. circumſtance is <hi>a ſubiecto loco,</hi> the place: namely, <hi>the ſea:</hi> the 3. <hi>ab adiunctis.</hi> for as S. <hi>Marke</hi> ſaith, there were alſo other <hi>ſhips</hi> with him: where <hi>per metonymiam ſubiecti,</hi> the hearers of Chriſt are vnderſtood, which were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in other ſhips.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Obſeruations and Doctrines.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ordinarie meanes to be vſed.</note>Ex. ver. 23. Chriſts entring into the ſhip, that he might ſaile ouer vnto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the lake, teacheth vs, that the ordinarie meanes appointed by God, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> they may be vſed,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat:</hi> 4. <hi>Deut:</hi> 6.16. <hi>Eccle:</hi> 3.27.</note> are not to be neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For it is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the Lord thy God.</hi> Mat. 4. Deut: 6.16. <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> amat periculu peribit in eo, He that loueth da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger ſhall periſh therin.</hi> Ecc: 3.27. <hi>And</hi> Aug
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19222:6"/> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>quis periculum, in quantum caueri poteſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>on caueret, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is deum tentaret quam in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m disperaret:</hi> for, <hi>nunquam periculum ſine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ericulo vincitur.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Aug:</note> 
                        <hi>He that auoideth not a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>er as much as in him lieth, rather temoteth God, then truſteth in him. For danger</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca<note place="margin">Seneca.</note>) is neuer ouercome without danger.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Againe,<note place="margin">Like the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which appeare beautifull to the eye, but within are full of ſtink, and rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> he entred not into a ſtately Marchants ſhip, but into a litle fiſhers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oate, that he might teach vs to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he pompe &amp; glory of the world: ſeeing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Lord of al, ſhewed his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f, &amp; that we ſhould imbrace humilitie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd lowlines of minde, which the world holdeth moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temptible. The glory of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his world is like a ſower grape, or vnripe fruit, which ſetteth <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                        </hi> teeth on edge: the diuell ſheweth the greene ſide, but hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the bitternes, vntill it be taſted.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. In that the Diſciples followed Chriſt into the ſhip, where they were in great danger and perill of their liues, we are taught what is the nature of true loue,<note place="margin">The nature of true loue</note> to cleaue faſt vnto Chriſt, as well in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, as proſperitie, that we ſuffer not our ſelues for any worldly reſpect to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from Chriſt. The vſe is,<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> that we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt in all temptations &amp; dangers.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19222:7"/> Among the thornes, that is, in tribulati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, croſſes, and afflictions: Chriſt is ſoo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt found,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant:</hi> 2.2.</note> which is a <hi>Lilie among thorne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> rather then in the Meadowes and green paſtures of pleaſure.<note place="margin">Similie.</note> But many are lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vnto the lazie hunting hound, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> follow <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                        </hi> game vnto the brake &amp; thorns but no farther, for feare of pricking him ſelfe, when yet the wilde beaſt is ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> more eaſily taken: So many will follow Chriſt in the ioyfull and pleaſant time o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> proſperitie, which in the troubleſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> times of perſecution forſake him. Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> follow him on the land ſecurely whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> they feare no danger, but fewe in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> troubled ſeas, and ſtormie waues of ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſitie, as the Apoſtles doe, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſturdie ſtormes of aduerſitie ariſe, they by and by ſhrinke away.<note place="margin">Simile.</note> All ſuch I may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare vnto thoſe that lend money vnto Marchants, vpon condition to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of their gain, but not of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> loſſes.</p>
                     <p>Here againe is repreſented vnto v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the nature of true friendſhip which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhould holde with men in the world,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ature of true friendſhip.</note> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> at all times keepe our faith and fidelitie with our friend, after the example of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19222:7"/> 
                        <hi>App:</hi> which followed Chriſt, as well by ſea, as land.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro:</hi> 17.</note> For as that Mirour of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſaith wiſely, <hi>A friend loueth at all times, and a brother is borne for aduerſitie.</hi> But alas this friendſhip is too common in the world, whereof the wiſe man ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, Ecc. 6.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ecc:</hi> 6.</note> 
                        <hi>Some man is a friend for his owne occaſion, and will not abide in time of trouble. Againe, ſome friend is but a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at the table, and in the day of affliction continueth not.</hi> This true friendſhip can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be but, <hi>inter bonos,</hi> among good men, (ſaith <hi>Cicero.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cicero.</note>) And when a man in proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie is beloued, it is vncertaine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the man, or his proſperitie be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and who ſo in aduerſitie forſaketh his neighbour, ſheweth plainly that he was neuer his friend. And ſo, as <hi>Petrach</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Petrach.</note> ſaith truly, <hi>non fides eſt ſublata, ſed fictio,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">De reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs vtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae.</note> His fidelitie which he neuer had, is not loſt, but his diſſimulation detected. Such kind of friends loue their neighbours as the dogge loueth his bone, which is, as long as he findeth any fleſh or ſweetnes about it, and when that faileth,<note place="margin">Like a dog with his bone.</note> he forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it. I haue read a tale, (but it hath a true morall) of a certaine man that had three eſpeciall friends, whom he inuited
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19222:8"/> to dinner, and at the end of the dinner, ſet before them three apples, euery one in ſome part corrupt and rotten; The firſt friend would not ſo much as touch them, whom therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected from the number of his friends. The ſecond did take one of the apples: and deuoured both the ſound part, and rotten together: whom he reputed as a foole, and therefore vnfit for friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. But the third, did take one of the apples, and did eate the ſound part, but left that which was rotten and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt: and him onely of the three, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained among the number of his friends. Theſe three friends, ſignifie ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie kindes of men, whereof ſome are ſo obdurate in malice, that though a man be neuer ſo vertuous,<note place="margin">Non amo te (Sabidi) nec poſſum dicere qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Martial. Li. <hi>2.</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram <hi>33.</hi>
                        </note> neuer ſo kinde, though he haue neuer ſo many good parts, yet they cannot loue him, ſpeake well of him, nor patiently indure to heare him commended. Such a one was <hi>Saul,</hi> who for the praiſe that the women gaue <hi>Dauid,</hi> after his victorie againſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> conceiued deadly diſpleaſure againſt him. 1. Sam: 18.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam:</hi> 18.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is a ſecond kind of men, that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19222:8"/> are ſo infatuated through inordinate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oue of their friend, that they approue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd defend all the actions of their friend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndifferently, good or euill, and know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot how to diuide the corruptions, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he ſound partes. There is alſo a third <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inde, which wiſely and diſcreetly loue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n their neighbours their vertues, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ate their vices; commend them in their well doings, but winke not at their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes; and thoſe onely are the loyall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd true friends.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The ſecond part.</head>
                     <p>THus much for the firſt part, namely,<note place="margin">The Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis of the ſecond part.</note> the circumſtances. Now to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, which deſcribeth the tempeſt which aroſe Chriſt being in the ſhip. The <hi>Analyſis</hi> whereof is:</p>
                     <p>Firſt he deſcribeth it, <hi>A cauſa procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ante, which was a great ſtorme of winde,</hi> as the <hi>Euangeliſt: Mar:</hi> the 4. and <hi>Luc:</hi> the 8. doe witnes.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, It is deſcribed from the effects, <hi>the waues daſhed into the ſhip, ſo that it was now full</hi> (ſaith Marc:) <hi>and the ſhip was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19222:9"/> couered with waues,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.37.</note> (ſaith this Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt.) Third, <hi>ab accident, inopinato,</hi> that this happened, <hi>Chriſt</hi> being a <hi>ſheepe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Obſer. and doctrines.</note>Firſt here I obſerue, (in that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were no ſooner with Chriſt in the ſhip, but preſently troubles, dangers, and tempeſts followed them,) That God in his mercifull prouidence, permitteth tribulations and aduerſities, to fall vpon his beſt beloued, either to ſhew his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory afterwards through their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, or that he might ſtirre vp his elect the more to gratitude, and the loue of God.<note place="margin">God hath reſpect of three things in afflicting his children,</note> And ſurely moſt ſweet is the prouidence of God towards his children in afflicting them, and that in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; Firſt, for the exerciſing of the vertue of patience: Secondly, for their greater prouocation to the loue of God: Thirdly, for the more ſignification of the loue of God towards them. For ſeeing that patience to euery action of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">Virtus in arduis.</note> is no leſſe neceſſarie then is breade to all kinde of meates: (becauſe pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ouercommeth all difficulties which are naturally incident to the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vertue, as bread giueth a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and taſte to all other meates) ſo the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19222:9"/> vertue of patience is euer needfull and very neceſſarie,<note place="margin">Similies.</note> as a certayne inſtrument by which wee worke all other vertues. And euen as a ſword which hath beene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ong in the ſcabert, becommeth ſo ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tie, that ſometime a man is wounded or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>layne of his aduerſarie before hee can draw it: So our patience, if it be not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, oftentimes giueth the Diuell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eaue to wound the ſoule, before it can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rme it ſelfe againſt any difficultie or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>emptation. And for this cauſe God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rciſeth his children with outward tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ulations, that they may bee the more ſtrong againſt all inward temptations: And therefore our Sauiour ſuffered his Diſciples to bee toſſed and endangered on the ſea,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> that hee might exerciſe them to patience, againſt the perſecutors of the faith, or againſt the aſſaults of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall enemies of the ſoule. That tree is not ſolide and firme which ſtandeth in the low watry valley, and neuer proued the winds and tempeſts: for the agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the windes maketh it to take more firme and deepe roote. So thoſe men are delicate and weake to ſuffer afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which were neuer before practiſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19222:10"/> in the ſchoole of aduerſitie.<note place="margin">Simil.</note> The <hi>Tyro</hi> or young ſouldier, looketh pale at the leaſt ſuſpition of a wound; but the <hi>Veteranus</hi> &amp; old ſouldier, boldly indureth the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die brunts of battell: which after blood hath often won the field.<note place="margin">Simile.</note> We ſee the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant horſes, whom nature hath framed for the courſe &amp; warres; if they be kept long in the ſtable idle, they become la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie, and full of diſeaſes, and lame. Iron through vſe becommeth bright.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Aſſiduo ſplendore micat, vultuque ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti,</l>
                        <l>Audet ad argenti deus aſpirare ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum.</l>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Mantua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>us.</note>The yron with continuall vſe, is brandiſhed ſo bright,</l>
                        <l>That it contends with ſiluer pure, in luſtre to the ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>But lying long in the earth, it gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ruſte, and is turned into earth: So vertue, being not ſtirred vp by affliction, droupeth, withereth, and fadeth. Hee that is tempted, afflicted, and vexed, whether it bee by Sathan,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> wicked men, or by God himſelfe ſtriking him: If he be gold, hee is purged and purified: If he bee ſiluer, hee becommeth more
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19222:10"/> bright: If he be yron, he loſeth his ruſte: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut we (ſayth a Father) <hi>Quia ferrum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>us quam aurum ſumus;</hi> Becauſe wee be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ron, rather then gold, (for the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arte) great tribulation is profitable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nto vs, for the caſting off the ruſte of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nne. And hereby God ſheweth, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey are more deare vnto him, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ee permitteth, for the good of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oules, to bee exerciſed with affliction. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or when God was angry with the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aelites, hee ſayd; <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.</note> 
                        <hi>I will lay my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ineyard waſte, it ſhall not bee digged nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>runed:</hi> And this pruning is by croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es and tribulations, which maketh it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he more fruitfull.<note place="margin">S. Baſill.</note> As <hi>Saint Baſil</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie learnedly obſerueth vpon that place; The tree that it may grow and fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie the better, muſt ſuffer many inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and bee deſpoyled of many ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous branches. To conclude,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> the ſweet Aromatical gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, except they be brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the peſtle, yeeldeth not their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doriferous ſmelles; ſo many thinges are there <hi>in rerum natura,</hi> in the nature of things, which teach the neceſſarie vſe of afflictions in the godly: &amp; layeth before our eies this of the <hi>Apoſtle;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> 
                        <hi>That tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19222:11"/> bringeth forth patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. That tribulation inciteth vs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> more to loue God, and to cleaue vnt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> him, it is apparant by this place: for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Apoſtles ſeeing themſelues in danger o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the ſea, ranne preſently to Chriſt, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> awooke him,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hom.</hi> 20.</note> ſaying; <hi>Lord ſaue vs, we pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſh:</hi> Well, (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>Deus tribula<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiones irruere permittit, vt ad eum frequenti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us confugiamus; God permitteth tribulati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons to fall vpon vs, that wee may the more of ten flie vnto him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Simile.</note>As the louing parents, ſeeing thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> children often to goe from them, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> play with their equalles, cauſeth thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſeruants to make them afraide, that they may runne (for feare) into their mother boſome: So God not onely ſuffereth v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to be vexed by others, but alſo himſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſometime ſtriketh vs, that hee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce vs vnto him, when we ſinfully go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> aſtray from him. Euen as the rayne fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling into the earth, cauſeth the ſeede to ſpring; ſo tribulation and affliction, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into our minde, erecteth our deſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and loue to God. And as a trauelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> walketh moſt warily,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> when hee trauel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth in dangerous deſarts, infeſted wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19222:11"/> thieues, but going in the populous and ſafe places he is moſt ſecure: ſo in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and afflictions wee gather our ſelues together, tread more warilie in our walkes, conſider more attentiuely the will of God, and implore the aide of God: and ſo tribulation exciteth and ſtirreth vs vp to the greater loue of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Thirdly, tribulations ſent from God, are an vndoubted ſigne of his loue towards vs; as it is manifeſt by this hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie: For what might bee more deare vnto Chriſt then his <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> who more innocent? who more holy? which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke all, that they might follow Chriſt. Yet he ſuffered them to bee in perill at ſea, and ſo to be toſſed that <hi>the ſhippe was euen couered with waues;</hi> ſo that they were ſo neere vnto death, that they might ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi> perſecuted by <hi>Saul; There is but a ſteppe betweene me and death:</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.</note> But all this was a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of his loue: For when the Lord would proue and crowne his beſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued children, the way to the crowne, and the manner of their probation is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and tribulation. God can take from vs all things that are grieuous; (as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19222:12"/> 
                        <hi>Chryſ.</hi> wiſely ſayeth;<note place="margin">Chryſ. ad popu. Anti.</note> 
                        <hi>Hom.</hi> 4 <hi>ad popu. Antio.</hi>) but vntill hee ſeeth vs purged of our ſinnes, &amp; our conuerſation vpright, he diſſolueth not the tribulation.<note place="margin">Simil.</note> The Goldſmith, vntill he ſeeth his gold pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, taketh it not out of the furnace The Muſition leaueth not ſtrayning o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> his ſtrings, vntill he perceiueth a perfect conſent of harmonie: So God taketh not away the cloude of affliction, before he ſeeth the amendment of our liues.<note place="margin">Ioſephs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. Haec Chry. Gen. <hi>37.24.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> was moſt innocent among all the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob;</hi> yet all the reſt liuing quietly at home in proſperitie, he onely was afflicted: Hee was caſt into a pitte, where he was like to periſh with famine: from thence he was drawne vp and ſold for a bondſlaue to the <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſe</hi> 28.</note> which caried him into <hi>Egipt,</hi> where againe hee was ſolde to <hi>Potiphar:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.1.</note> then greuouſlie tempted to adulterie, which he reſiſted, keeping moſt chaſtly his fidelitie vnto God and his Maiſter;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Verſe</hi> 7.20.</note> yet falſly accuſed, he was condemned and caſt into priſon, where he remayned a long time: Hee was deceiued by the vngratefull chiefe Butler.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 40. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 23.</note> But to what end was all this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction? that by this meanes he might
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19222:12"/> bee exalted by <hi>Pharao,</hi> and bee made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ord of Egypt, and that by him, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ather, Brethren, and all the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f God might bee relieued in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reame of famine,<note place="margin">God is a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> which hee could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er haue done, except hee had firſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ered this affliction in Egypt. Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>akefull prouidence neuer fayled here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n; as hee himſelfe ſayd to his Brethren; <hi>Now then you ſent me not hither but GOD; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ut to what end? to preſerue your poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ie in this land, and to ſaue you aliue. Gen.</hi> 45.<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</hi> Ioſephs exaltation.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>But ſee now how bountifullie the Lord rewarded euery one of theſe afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ions which he ſuffered: For the hatred of his Brethren, God gaue him fauour with <hi>Pharao</hi> and his Princes: For that his Brethren contemned and mocked him, ſaying; <hi>Behold this Dreamer commeth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. <hi>Gen.</hi> 43. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 26. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 40.42.43.45.</note> he was honored of them, <hi>bowing downe to the ground before him.</hi> For his exile, he was exalted in a ſtrange land: For the labour of his hands in ſeruing <hi>Potiphar,</hi> he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a ring fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Kings owne hand: For his fetters &amp; chaines in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored with a chaine of gold: For his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticoloured coat which his brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tooke
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19222:13"/> from him, the King arrayed him with Princely Roabes: For that hee miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them that were bound in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in great dignitie he miniſtered vnto the King: For the priſon and the dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, he was carried in a Princely Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot: For that he was deſpiſed of all men as a ſtranger and a ſeruant, hee was ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of all men with bowing knees <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> For contemning the vnlawfull pleaſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of adulterie, hee tooke to his wife a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble woman: For the loſſe of his father<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> houſe, he was made Ruler ouer all <hi>Egipt</hi> Who ſeeth not heere, that theſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that God ſendeth to his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> were ſignes of Gods tende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> loue towards his children, in him, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he aduanced him. To conclude, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions therefore are ſignes of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlie fauour, and not of his hatred to his elect: <hi>For the Lord correcteth him whom he loueth, as the father doth the child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> in whom he delighteth:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
                        <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.12.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                        <hi>Ideo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muntur, vt preſſi clament, clamantes exau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diantur, exauditi deum glorificent.</hi> They are therefore afflicted, that being afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they might call vpon God, that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon God, they might bee heard
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19222:13"/> that being heard, they might glorifie God. And therefore well ſayth <hi>Seneca,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
                        <hi>Miſeri ſunt qui nunquam miſeri fuerunt;</hi> They are wretched which neuer were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n miſerie.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This ſhippe, wherein were Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd his Diſciples,<note place="margin">The Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall ſenſe.</note> 
                        <hi>Allegoricallie</hi> repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eth the Church militant in this life: The Church is as a ſhippe toſſed on the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>urbulent ſeas of this world: the godly, elect, and faithfull, are carryed in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hip. The boiſterous windes, ſtormes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd waues, are diuers vexations, tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ations, and perſecutions, wherewith the godly in this life are perſecuted: and theſe are rayſed vp of Sathan, and his band; as Tyrants, Perſecutors, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, and wicked men, which ſo riſe vp in furie againſt the Church, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it ſeemeth to bee oppreſſed and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extinguiſhed,<note place="margin">It is to be doubted whether they that commit themſelues to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the waters, be to be reckoned among the liuing.</note> ſo that to the world they ſeeme (as <hi>Anacharſis</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Anacharſis.</note> ſaid once of Nauigators; <hi>Dubitatum fuerit, inter vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uos ne habendi, qui vitam vndarum, vento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> arbitrio committerent.</hi> In theſe ſtormes of afflictions the godly ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time begin to faint, eſpecially when they ſee the ſhippe euen couered with waues:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19222:14"/> But our <hi>Archinauclerus</hi> is Chriſt, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſometime ſeemeth to ſleepe, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hee doth not preſently deliuer his chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, but ſuffereth them awhile to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> afflicted. To him in all our miſeries, <hi>tanquam ad aſylum;</hi> as vnto a Sanctuari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> we muſt flie, and awake him with our prayers, ſaying; <hi>Lord ſaue vs.</hi> It is growne into a common prouerbe; <hi>Qui neſcit ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re diſcat nauigare;</hi> He that knoweth not how to pray, let him learne to ſayle, which our ſpirituall nauigation,<note place="margin">Affliction teacheth to pray.</note> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the ſeas of affliction, teacheth; then Chriſt being ſtirred vp by prayer, calmeth the tempeſt of tribulation by the power of his word, &amp; changeth all things into a ioyfull <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie.</p>
                     <p>The vſe<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> is, that wee be not offended at the ſmalneſſe of Chriſts number, when wee ſee the greater part to walke the broad way to deſtruction; when we ſee many to reſiſt the truth; and with <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> obiect vnto vs; <hi>Quota pars orbis mortalium vos eſtis? What a ſmall parte of the world are yee Chriſtians?</hi> Chriſts flocke is <hi>a little flocke: Luk.</hi> 12.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.</note> Perſecutions (ſaith <hi>Nazianzene</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Nazian.</note>) <hi>Chriſtianiſmum nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorem
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19222:14"/> potius quam debiliorem reddunt: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Chriſtianitie rather nobler then weaker.</hi> And theſe are the notes of the true Church: <hi>Ioa.</hi> 15.16.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. And as Chriſt ſlept in the moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icill dangers of the Apoſtles; ſo in the midſt of their afflictions and anguiſhes, Chriſt ſeemeth ſometime to the godlie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o ſleepe, when hee doth not haſten to deliuer them. Hence ſprang theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed cryes of the godlie; <hi>Lord, careſt thou not that wee periſh? Mar.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.</note> 
                        <hi>Lord how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ong wilt thou delay? Pſa.</hi> 6.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſa.</hi> 6.</note> 
                        <hi>and Pſa.</hi> 13.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſa.</hi> 13.</note> 
                        <hi>How long wilt thou forget me Lord for euer? How long wilt thou hide thy face from mee? But in very deede,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſa.</hi> 121.</note> 
                        <hi>hee that keepeth Iſrael will neither ſlumber nor ſleepe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It is ſurely a wonder (ſaith one) that he, of whom it is ſayd; <hi>He that keepeth Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſhall nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>her ſlumber nor ſleepe: Pſa.</hi> 121.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſa.</hi> 121.</note> is yet now ſayde to ſleepe. What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this ſleepe? 1. Hee ſleepeth, that he might ſhew the veritie of his humane nature. This was a true, not a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit ſleepe, which watching and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſome labour did enforce; carrying an humane body, ſubiect to ſuch affections as our mortall bodies are. 2. God is ſayd to ſleepe, eyther when he doth not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19222:15"/> preſently helpe the godly, or puniſh the wicked: According to this of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: Pſa.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Vp Lord, why ſleepeſt thou<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> awake,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſa.</hi> 44.</note> 
                        <hi>and bee not abſent from vs for euer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> Againe, he is ſayd to <hi>Ariſe,</hi> eyther when he deliuereth the righteous, or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the wicked: As hee ſayeth againe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. <hi>The Lord awaked as one out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> a ſleepe,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſa.</hi> 78.</note> 
                        <hi>and ſmote his enemies in the hinde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> parts, and put them to perpetuall ſhame.</hi> The Lord therefore is ſayd to ſleepe, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> he ſeemeth for a time to winke at the miſeries of the godly, and the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the vngodly, becauſe he exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeth hereby the patience of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and expecteth the conuerſion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the wicked.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> 
                        <hi>The bountifulnes of the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> leadeth thee to repentance: Rom.</hi> 2. Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is ſaid to ſleepe when faith fainteth, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is cooled, and the feare of God an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> deuotion is extinguiſhed in vs; then the windes of wicked deſires ariſe; as am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, couetouſneſſe, &amp;c. which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the tranquillitie of the minde, and threaten deſtruction to the ſoule, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Chriſt bee awake,</hi> by feruent and faithfull prayer.</p>
                     <p>He can no more forget his elect, then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19222:15"/> a mother can her childe. It is ſayde of <hi>Ioſeph: Gen.</hi> 39.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.</note> 
                        <hi>That God was with him in priſon.</hi> For <hi>Ioſeph</hi> loſt not his faith and hope in God, neither when hee was caſt into the pit; neyther when hee was a bond ſlaue, neither when he was caſt into priſon, at which time (in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man) God was fartheſt off from him; yet Gods prouidence neuer ſlept, but followed him when hee was in the pit, and neuer forſooke him in priſon, nor in all his aduerſities. It was God that helde the hand of his angry Maiſter, that he ſhould not kill him vpon ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of defiling his wife. And ſo Gods watchfull eye, though hee ſeemed to ſleepe, euer waked with <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> So was God euer with <hi>Iacob,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.13. <hi>Gen.</hi> 29. <hi>Gen.</hi> 30. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.</note> in all his brunts of affliction: He was with him in his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> that hee might di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him in the way. Hee was with him when he ſerued <hi>Laban,</hi> that hee might multiplie his flocke. Hee was with him in his returne,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.</note> leaſt wrathfull <hi>Laban</hi> ſhould draw him backe. Hee was with him at his entring into his natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, leaſt hee ſhould bee oppeſſed by <hi>Eſau.</hi> To conclude, hee was with him when he went downe into <hi>Egypt,</hi> as hee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19222:16"/> promiſed:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.</note> 
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 46. <hi>I will goe downe with thee into Egypt, and I will alſo bring thee vp ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> And thus (brethren) ye ſee that Gods mercifull prouidence neuer ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth towards his children.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">A queſtion.</note>Why then doth hee ſleepe? why doth he hide himſelfe? Why doth he deferre to helpe and ſuccour his children in their diſtreſſe?</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The anſwer</note>The anſwere is eaſie: 1. That being deſtitute of all ſuccour &amp; helpe of man, the godly might acknowledge him to be the onely and opportunate helper in all their affliction: <hi>Pſa.</hi> 9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.15. <hi>Hee ſhall call vpon me, and I will heare him; I will bee with him in trouble and deliuer him.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.15.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. That hee might proue them, &amp; the more prouoke them to craue his ayde.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That hee might trie their conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; <hi>Et quaſi igne excoctos iuſtiores et purio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res faciat.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hiero. ſub. Hab.</note> 
                        <hi>Hiero. ſup. Hab.</hi> And as it were by purifying them in the fire, make them more cleane and pure.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Then the Lord ſeemeth to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to ſleepe, when hee permitteth them ſo to bee plunged in calamities, that all hope of eſcaping being taken away, his mercy may be the more welcome when
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19222:16"/> it commeth:<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
                        <hi>Vt tardius dans dona ſua com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendet, non neget; ſaith Aug.</hi> That by his ſlownes in giuing, he might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend, &amp; denie his gifts vnto vs. <hi>Deſiderata diu dulcius obtinentur, cito data vileſcunt;</hi> Things long deſired, are the more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant being obtayned, and what is eaſilie gotten, is vilely eſteemed.</p>
                     <p>Againe, <hi>Aug.</hi> in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 55. ſayth;<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſa. <hi>55.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Forte nauis tua ideo turbatur quia Chriſtus in te dormit;</hi> Perchance thy ſhippe is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled becauſe Chriſt ſleepeth in thee. And Chriſt ſleepeth in them whoſe faith ſleepeth; <hi>Excita Chriſtum, recole fidem;</hi> Awake Chriſt, recall thy faith.</p>
                     <p>To conclude this part; This ſleepe of Chriſt after the weariſome labours of his miniſterie, teacheth vs: 1. That our naturall ſleepe, that refreſheth our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies after labour, ſo it exceede not the meane, is not diſpleaſing vnto God.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>Quod caret alternare quie durabile no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt.</l>
                        <l>Without ſucceeding reſt, be ſure</l>
                        <l>No creature long may toyle endure.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p n="2">2. The veritie of his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hereby appeareth; Hee hungred: <hi>Math.</hi> 4. He was wearie: <hi>Ioa.</hi> 4. Hee wept: <hi>Io.</hi> 11. and tooke vpon him all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19222:17"/> our infirmities, and was true man, ſinne onely excepted. For theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are competent and agreeable to our humane nature; which maketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Marcionites, Maniches, Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and other ſuch Heretikes which denie <hi>Chriſts</hi> true humanitie. 3. That Chriſt watcheth ouer vs ſleeping, and by his Angels keepeth and preſerueth vs: <hi>Pſa.</hi> 121. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Pars tertia.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The analy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis or reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the 3. part.</note>THe alaying and calming of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt is deſcribed: 1. <hi>A cauſa efficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te impulſiua,</hi> which was the petition of the Diſciples: the forme whereof is expreſſed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. this is amplyfied by the <hi>adiunct puſillanimitie</hi> of the Diſciples. 2. The primarie efficient cauſe was Chriſt himſelfe. 3. The manner, or the inſtrumentall cauſe is deſcribed, which was the rebuking of the windes and the ſea: the forme whereof is ſet downe: <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.39. <hi>Peace and be ſtill.</hi> Laſtly, the forme of the miracle is expreſſed, which is, that at the words of Chriſt the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt ceaſed, which is amplified by the effect
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19222:17"/> and <hi>adiunct</hi> there; <hi>and there followed a great calme.</hi> So much for the <hi>analyſis,</hi> now to the obſeruations and doctrines.</p>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>Obſeruations and Doctrines.</head>
                        <p n="1">1. Firſt, we are here taught in all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, afflictions, and neceſſities, to flie vnto Chriſt, and to call vpon him by feruent prayer; if we would that Chriſt ſhould awake and heare vs, it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that we our ſelues ſhould firſt be awaked, and deuoutly pray vnto him: yea for this cauſe he ſendeth tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that he might awake and ſtirre vs vp to conſider our miſerie and the eſtate wherein we are, that we might after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards awake God with our prayers. So dealt he with his beloued Apoſtles, euen he that <hi>bringeth forth the winde out of his treaſures.</hi> Pſ: 135. it was he that ſtirred vp this tempeſt, &amp; ſtrooke this feare into his Diſciples, that feare might prouoke them to pray, &amp; that their prayer might ſtirre vp Chriſt to ſhew this miracle, whereby they and all his elect might be the better confirmed in the faith. This promiſe he hath plighted, this law of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19222:18"/> mercy he hath left vnto vs: <hi>Come vnto me all ye that labour and I will refreſh you, call vpon me in the time of trouble, and I will heare you.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Mat:</hi> 11. Similies.</note> The Shepheard is quickly ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp at the voyce of his ſheepe, the louing mother, at the crie of her childe, the henne at the noiſe of her young, and to all theſe God in holy ſcripture is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. So King <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> being inuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with an huge hoſte of his enemies, prayed vnto the Lord, ſaying: <hi>There is no ſtrength in vs to ſtand before this great multitude that commeth againſt vs, neither doe we knowe what to doe, but to lift vp our eyes vnto thee,</hi> 2. Chro: 20.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro:</hi> 20.</note> And he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of God a maruellous victorie. So the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth 1. Pet: 5.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.</note> 
                           <hi>Caſt all your care vpon him, for he careth for you,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</note> and Phillip. 4. <hi>be nothing carefull but in all things let your requeſt be ſhewed vnto God in prayer and ſupplication with gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Simile.</note> For as it grieueth not the nurſe whoſe breaſts are full of milke when the childe ſucketh them, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eaſeth and delighteth her: ſo he is not troubleſome to the moſt plentifull goodnes of God, but very acceptable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19222:18"/> vnto him, which offereth vnto him oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſhew mercy; this mercy of God moſt prone and readie to ſuccour all them that call vpon him, the Lord commendeth vnto the faithfull, ſaying; Mat. 7.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Mat:</hi> 7.</note> 
                           <hi>If ye that are euill can giue vnto your children good gifts, how much more ſhall your heauenly father giue good things to them that aske him?</hi>
                           <note place="margin">A comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</note> Who then would euer deſpaire of his cauſe? who would not expect a moſt certaine victorie, when the iudge himſelfe exhorteth the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe to craue, and preſcribeth him a forme of crauing, and promiſeth that he ſhall eaſily obtaine? And this doth our Iudge Ieſus Chriſt, that we might ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all difficulties, he exhorteth vs to aske, hee teacheth vs a forme of prayer, and promiſeth againe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Aske and you ſhall receiue.</hi> Mat: 7.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>This example of the Diſciples there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore teacheth vs, what wee ſhould doe when we are preſſed downe with the waters of tribulations, which when they ſawe the imminent danger of death before their eyes, they cried vnto the Lord, ſleeping, <hi>Lord ſaue vs, we periſh:</hi>
                           <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19222:19"/> for prayer is the common refuge of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmities. And therefore a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ancient father (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) ſaid; that Phyſitions did vſe many kindes of medicines,<note place="margin">Prayer the medicine for all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies.</note> according to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> varietie of the diſeaſes of their Patients but for the expelling of all diſeaſes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the ſoule, for the vndergoing of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities of this life, prayer is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> onely remedie and common medicine becauſe it draweth the <hi>omnipotent</hi> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> vnto it, who onely is the ſoueraigne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, for euery maladie. The efficacie of prayer, the ancient Fathers could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſufficiently commend: <hi>Auguſtine</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Prayer <hi>clauem coeli,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Aug: ſer:</hi> 226. <hi>de temp.</hi> 1. <hi>Regum.</hi> 18.38.45.</note> the keye of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. With this keye <hi>Eliah</hi> opened hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and brought downe fire which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the ſacrifice, and alſo with his prayers, cauſed the heauen to powre downe raine to make the earth fruitfull. An other calleth prayer <hi>tabulam naufra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorum, the table or planke for ſuch as ſuffer ſhipwracke in the ſeas of temptations of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> life,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> which in the dangerous ſeas and waues of this world carieth vs ſafe vnto the hauen of all happines. <hi>Chryſoſtom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> calleth it <hi>animae ſolem, the ſunne of the ſoule</hi>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19222:19"/> becauſe as the ſunne inlightneth the world, ſo prayer illuminateth the mind. Innumerable almoſt are the examples both in holy ſcriptures, and other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of all ages, which manifeſt the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull efficacie of prayer, but at this time, this ſhall ſuffice.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Ex. verſ. 26. In that the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued his Diſciples, for their diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full feare, ſaying, <hi>Why are ye fearefull ô ye of litle faith?</hi> We are taught in the middeſt of our tribulations and miſeries, neuer to ſuffer our confidence and truſt in God to quaile. The Diſciples were not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faith, for in this preſent danger they called vpon the Lord, which they could neuer haue done, except they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued that he could haue holpen them. Yet their faith was but litle, as it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by their diſtruſtfull feare: for as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue <hi>caſteth out all feare,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Io:</hi> 4.</note> ſo a perfect faith expelleth all timerous diſtruſt, and crieth with the <hi>Prophet,</hi> Pſ: 27.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſ:</hi> 27.</note> 
                           <hi>The Lord is my light and ſaluation, whom then ſhall I feare? the Lord is the ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ngth of my life, of whom ſhall I be afraide?</hi> Some by the word <hi>[faith]</hi> vnderſtand, <hi>confidence</hi> or <hi>truſt,</hi> and take it <hi>metonymicos,</hi> whereby the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19222:20"/> 
                           <hi>cauſe</hi> is taken for the <hi>effect,</hi> for a ſtrong faith bringeth foorth confidence. And therefore ſome tranſlate it, <hi>exigua fiducia praediti, endued with litle confidence.</hi> And worthily our Sauiour reproued them of their diffidence: for they that had ſeene ſo often the Diuinitie and power of Chriſt, confirmed with ſo many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, what cauſe had they to feare? as if he were not the ſame God on the ſeas as on the land: And ſurely many ſuch there are at this day, which though they haue oftentimes, proued Gods aide in their tribulations, yet if any new thing happen vnto them, they by and by murmur againſt God, and diſtruſt his goodnes: and as the world is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with them, ſo withall their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is changed. Such were the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull ſpeeches of the wicked, which are mentioned, Pſ: 78.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.</note> 
                           <hi>They ſpeake againſt God, ſaying; Can God prepare a table in the wildernes? he ſmote indeed the rocke that the waters guſhed out, but can he giue bread alſo, or prepare fleſh for his people?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>We ſee that ſometime it chanceth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, that an enemie (if he be of any generous and heroicall nature) ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coureth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19222:20"/> an enemie, that in extremitie flieth vnto him for ſuccour, reputing it an honor vnto him; How much more will God protect &amp; defend them which humblie flie vnto him in their extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and miſeries? Let vs therefore hold faſt in all our miſeries, <hi>our confidence in God, as an anſwere of the ſoule both ſure and ſtedf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſt</hi> Heb: 6.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.</note> And againe, he ſaid vnto them which ſuffered for Chriſts ſake, the ſpoyling of their goods: <hi>Caſt not away your confidence which hath great recompence of reward,</hi> Heb: 10.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.</note> Surely all godly men, in their greateſt affliction, holde faſt this confidence. So holy <hi>Iob</hi> in the midſt of his calamities ſaid: <hi>Though he ſhould ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him:</hi> Iob. 13.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Iob.</hi> 13.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is recorded by <hi>Aeneas Siluius,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Aeneas Siluius in hiſto. Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</note> 
                           <hi>in hiſto: Bohem.</hi> of <hi>Wenceſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> that when his great armie was vanquiſhed, his power ſubdued, and himſelfe taken priſoner: being asked how it fared with him, anſwered ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer better, for when I was guarded and inuironed with the aide of man, I had ſcarce any leiſure to thinke vpon God: but now being deſtitute of all humane ſuccours, I fixe my whole hope in God,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19222:21"/> who I know will not forſake me, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> will heare me when I call vpon him.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Out of verſ. 26. That faith in al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the Saints is not alike, and in the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> qualitie, but in ſome more and ſtronger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> and in ſome leſſe and weaker. This infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of the Diſciples is not ſet down<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to this end, that we ſhould flatter ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſelues in the like weakenes, but that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſhould labour by all meanes to ſtirre vp and ſtrengthen our faith by prayer, hearing of the word, holy meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>This example yeeldeth moſt ſweete conſolation to the weake and fearefull conſciences: for euen as Chriſt doth not reiect his Apoſtles ob: <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, ſo the Lord doth not deſpiſe the weake faith which apprehendeth Chriſt the <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,</hi> as his obiect, though it be not yet of the ſtrongeſt. Let none therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of the goodnes of God. <hi>For a brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed reede ſhall he not breake.</hi> Eſa: 42.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Eſa:</hi> 42.</note> but pray with the father of the poſſeſſed, Mrac: 9.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Marc:</hi> 9.</note> 
                           <hi>Lord helpe my vnbeliefe:</hi> and with the Apoſtles, Luc. 17.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Luc:</hi> 17.</note> 
                           <hi>Lord increaſe our faith:</hi> and then wil God make vs perfect, <hi>confirme, ſtrengthen and ſtabliſh vs.</hi> 1. Pet. 5.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19222:21"/>
                        <p>Let vs beware therfore of diffidence, and diſtruſt, and by all meanes abandon all doubtfulnes of Gods grace, mercy, and free remiſſion of our ſinnes. To di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt is, <hi>Firſt to make God a lyar.</hi> 1. Ioh. 5.10.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.10.</note> 2. It fighteth <hi>ex diametro,</hi> againſt faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n Gods promiſes, Rom: 4.16.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.16.</note> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ath of Almightie God, Ezech. 33.11.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Ezech.</hi> 33.11.</note> Ioh. 5.24.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.24.</note> Third, it is directly repugnant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o the true iuſtifying faith, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> and <hi>Hypoſtaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>,</hi> Heb: 11.1.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1.</note> and is oppoſed to doubtfulnes, Mat: 21.21.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Mat:</hi> 21.21.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which very pithily ſpeaketh S. <hi>Bernard: Tria conſidero in quibus tola ſpes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nea conſiſtit, charitatem adoptionis,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">S. Bern:</note> 
                           <hi>verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>em promiſionis, poteſtatem redditionis, &amp;c.</hi> I conſider three things in which my whole hope conſiſteth,<note place="margin">A ſweet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</note> Gods loue in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopting me, the truth of his promiſe, and his power to performe: let now my foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iſh cogitation murmure as much as it will, ſaying; What art thou? or how great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s that glory? or by what merits doeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hou hope to obtaine it? <hi>Et ego fiduciali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>er respondeo, Scio, Credo, Certus ſum;</hi> But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> will anſwere confidently; I knowe, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eleeue, I am certaine, <hi>quia in Charitate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>imia adoptauit me, quia verax in permiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19222:22"/> quia potens in exhibitione,</hi> Becauſe in his abundant loue he hath accepted me: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is true of his promiſe: Becauſe he is of power to performe.</p>
                        <p n="5">5. In that the waters at the word and command of Chriſt were ſilent, calme and ſtill; as it is an vndoubted argument of Chriſts Diuinitie, that he is the true, eternall and omnipotent God. We reade of <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rxis</hi> the mightie <hi>Monarch</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> that being about to paſſe ouer the ſea of <hi>Helleſponte,</hi> ſtrooke and beate the waues with his rodde, charging them, that they ſhould not preſume to riſe and ſwell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but to be calme; but the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters yeelding no reuerence to the king, nor obeying his ridiculous charge, kept their naturall courſe: But Chriſt the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> of heauen, <hi>who hath preſcribed to the waters their bounds which they ſhall not paſſe,</hi> Pſal. 104.9.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſ:</hi> 104.9.</note> 
                           <hi>whoſe word, the fire, and haile, ſnowe and vapours, ſtormie winde and tempeſt doe execute,</hi> Pſ: 148.8.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſ:</hi> 148.8.</note> commandeth the winde &amp; ſeas, and all his creatures, and they obey him. Let vs ſay therefore with <hi>Dauid, the Lord is on my ſide, I will not feare what man can doe vnto me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. To conclude, we haue here a moſt ſweete teſtimonie of the clemencie of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19222:22"/> our good God, who after the terrible te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſts of tribulations, ſendeth a ioyfull calme of tranquilitie and peace: So our Sauiour here, did not only heare his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him &amp; deliuered them out of all danger, but alſo ſhewed his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine power in commanding the windes and the ſea, &amp; his admirable goodnes &amp; loue, which in our greateſt miſeries is neareſt at hand to helpe vs. This happie end, &amp; <hi>cataſtrophe</hi> of our calamities and temptations, our louing God effecteth, if we truly truſt in him, <hi>Ye ſhall weepe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (ſaith he to his elect) <hi>but your ſorrow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>hall be turned into ioy,</hi> Ioh. 16.22.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.22.</note> Againe, <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>or a litle while haue I forſaken thee, but with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>reat compaſſion I will gather thee,</hi> Eſa: 54.7.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Eſa:</hi> 5.7.</note> This is the great calme that followeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he tempeſts of Gods Children. So <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ias</hi> after his blindnes receiued againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is ſight, paſſed the reſt of his life in ioy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd ſaw his childrens children. Tob. 14.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Tob:</hi> 14.</note> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o the Lord rewarded his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Iob,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>fter all his grieuous plagues and loſſes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſtored him twiſe ſo much: <hi>and after this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ued Iob an hundreth yeeres, and ſawe his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>nnes, and his ſonnes ſonnes, euen foure gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ations, Iob vltim.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Iob: vltim.</note> So <hi>Ioſeph</hi> after his exile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> impriſonment, was aduanced to great
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19222:23"/> honour: So <hi>Dauid</hi> after the long perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Saul:</hi> So <hi>Iacob</hi> after his long ſorrow for the loſſe of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> found exceeding ioy and proſperitie, Gen. 45.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Gen:</hi> 45.</note> So the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts of the godly againſt the fleſh, the diuell and allurements of the world, which are ſtormes, tempeſts, and windes, wherewith they are toſſed, on the vaſte ſea of this world, and indangered ſo that if Chriſt ſleepeth in them, they begin to ſinke, vnles by feruent prayer, they ſtirre vp their faith and confidence in him, that he may command &amp; rebuke the windes, that there may follow this pleaſant and wiſhed calme. This dutie of pietie if we performe, we may ioyfully ſay with the Prophet, Pſ. 18.6.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal:</hi> 18 6.</note> 
                           <hi>In my trouble I did call vpon the Lord, and cried vnto my God, and he heard my voyce out of his Temple, and my crie did come before him, euen into his eares.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſal:</hi> 94.</note> Pſ: 94.49. <hi>In the multitude of the ſorrowes which I had in my heart, thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts haue refreſhed my ſoule.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The fourth part.</head>
                     <p>THe fourth part, containeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent effects of this <hi>miracle.</hi> verſ. 27. Firſt, the peoples admiration of <hi>Chriſts power,</hi> Secondly, their extolling &amp;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19222:23"/> commending of the ſame, by adding an <hi>exclamation,</hi> and <hi>proſopopaeia:</hi> To which the <hi>Euangeliſts</hi> S. <hi>Marke</hi> and S. <hi>Luke,</hi> addeth a third, namely, <hi>their exceeding feare.</hi> Marc. 4.41. Luc: 8.25.</p>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>Obſeruations and Doctrines.</head>
                        <p n="7">7. Out of verſ: 27. By the example of the people which maruelled and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at <hi>Chriſt, vt hominem dormi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ntem,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Chryſoſt: in opere imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>rſ: hom: <hi>23.</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um imperantem, &amp; creaturam obedientem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome, ſleeping as a man, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding as a God, and the creature obeying,</hi> and extolling the Maieſtie and power of Chriſt: we are taught not curiouſly to ſearch the wonderfull workes of God, or careleſly to conſider of them, but in true ſimplicitie of heart, to admire and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them, and learne thereby the true feare of God, who is ſo wonderfull in all his workes, for <hi>ſcrutator maieſtatis, oppri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitur a gloria;</hi> ſaith <hi>Prosper: de vocation:</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Prosper. de vocatione. Gen.</note> 
                           <hi>gen: the curious ſearcher of the Maieſtie is oppreſſed of the glorie.</hi> And by the humble man that knocketh by prayer hath the doore opened vnto him to finde, which the raſh ſearcher into Gods ſecrets, in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19222:24"/> the proud ſpirit of curioſitie, ſhall neuer be able to finde out,<note place="margin">Bern: ſuper Cant: <hi>24.</hi>
                           </note> ſaith S. Bern:</p>
                        <p n="8">8 Againe, let vs learne here to obey him to whom all inſenſible creatures yeeld obedience. Hereof ſpeaketh the primeable Prophet, Pſal. 148.8.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſ.</hi> 148.8.</note> 
                           <hi>Praiſe ye the Lord, fire and haile, ſnowe and vapours, ſtormie winde, which execute his word.</hi> And is it not a wonder that all creatures with ſuch readines and conſtancie, ſhew their obedience to the Creator, and that man for whoſe ſake they were all created, ſhould in an ingratefull and obſtinate minde, perfidiouſly denie obedience to the Lord?</p>
                        <p>Therefore the Prophet Eſa. 1. verſ. 2.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Eſa:</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.</note> that he might taxe this ſhamefull obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie of mans heart, calleth heauen and earth to witnes againſt him, <hi>Heare ô hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and hearken ô earth, &amp;c. the oxe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owner, and the aſſe his maiſters crib, but</hi> Iſrael <hi>hath not knowne, &amp;c.</hi> As if he had ſaid: all you (ô my <hi>Creatures</hi>) are obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vnto my voyce, onely man is of a ſtubborne and diſobedient heart, and ye ſhall all be witneſſes againſt him; I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the ſea, and it was diuided in two partes, ſo that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> went
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19222:24"/> through as on drie land, the waters gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them free paſſage, Exod: 14.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Exod:</hi> 14.</note> I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the earth, and it opened her mouth and ſwallowed vp rebellious <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Dathan, and Abyram,</hi> Num: 16.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.</note> At my command the fire came out and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> Leuit: 10.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Leuit.</hi> 10.</note> I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the Sun at the prayers of <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> and it ſtood ſtil in the midſt of heauen to giue a glorious victorie vnto my people: Ioſh: 10.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Ioſhu:</hi> 10.</note> 
                           <hi>The earth trembled and quaked,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>the foundations alſo of the mountaines moued and ſhooke becauſe he was angrie</hi> Pſ: 18.7.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Pſ:</hi> 18.7.</note> 
                           <hi>when Chriſt ſuffered, the ſun was darkned, the rockes claue aſunder,</hi> Math: 27.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Mat:</hi> 17.</note> yet the heart of man harder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very ſtones will not be mollified.</p>
                        <p>Let man learne then obediently to ſerue the Lord,<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> and carefully frame him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to keepe his commandements, to whom the earth, the ſea, and the windes, the elements, and all vnreaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures obey, and execute his will.</p>
                        <p>Let vs learne here to magnifie, extoll,<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> &amp; praiſe the Lord, as often as we behold his goodnes, mercy and loue towards vs, when he keepeth vs in dangers, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth vs in tribulations, taketh vs out of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of our enemies, &amp; protecteth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19222:25"/> vs from the rage and power of Sathan, and inceſſantly, laude and glorifie his name, who <hi>hath called vs out of darknes into his maruellous light,</hi> 1. Pet. 29.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 29.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p n="9">9 Laſtly, we haue here a teſtimonie of the wonderfull prouidence of God, which plainely appeareth in this place, in confounding openly in the malignant practiſes of <hi>Sathan,</hi> the immortal enemie of God, and mankinde, and conuerting all his pernitious enterpriſes (maugre his rage and furie) to the benefite of his Church, and the good of his elect. In this tempeſt at ſea, Sathans practiſe was vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to roote out the name of the Lord and his glory, by drenching his ſhip in the floods, and drowning his followers. But by the admirable prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God it came to paſſe, that this tempeſt mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred matter of illuſtrating the glory of Chriſt, and extolling of his <hi>Godhead:</hi> For when <hi>Chriſt</hi> rebuked the winds, quieted the tempeſt, and calmed the ſea; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple rauiſhed with the admiration of his diuine maieſtie, and aſtoniſhed, <hi>cryed out, what man is this that commandeth, and both windes and ſea obey him?</hi> So the Diuell thought by his curſed mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19222:25"/> to burie Chriſt with the glory of his name in the ſepulchre, <hi>when they made the Sepulcher ſure with the watch, and ſealed the ſtone: Mat.</hi> 27.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>6.<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>6.</note> But all this (the wiſedome of God ſo diſpoſing) was ſo farre off from the obſcuring of <hi>Chriſtes glorie,</hi> that it made for the manifeſting of the ſame,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.11.</note> and confirmed the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his <hi>reſurrection, when the Keepers for feare of him being aſtonied, ranne into the Citie, and ſhewed vnto the High Prieſts all the things that were done: Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. <hi>and</hi> 11. Wherefore in all our miſeries and afflictions, and in the furies of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and his inſtruments, whiles we are toſſed on the tempeſtuous ſeas of this life, let vs with an aſſured confidence flie vnto the Father of all <hi>mercies</hi> and <hi>conſolation,</hi> awake him with our faithfull and deuoute prayers, who onely know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how, and is willing and able to alay all the ſtrormes of this troubleſome life, giue a ioyfull iſſue to our temptations, and at length to conduct vs to the ſafe ſhores and happy hauen of eternall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, where is the fulneſſe of ioy; and at his right hand are indeficient plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for euermore.</p>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:19222:26"/>
                        <p>To whom with the Soone and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons in one moſt glorious Trinitie, one God in vnitie, might and Maieſtie, be aſcribed all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, prayſe, power and dominion, now and for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:26"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:27"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:27"/>
                  <p>THE IVDGES AND IVRIES INSTRVCTION.</p>
                  <p>WITH A WARNING TO Witneſſes to ſhunne the horrible ſinne of Periurie: The greatneſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is here layde before them: Very neeeſſary for theſe times.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM EST, <hi>Preacher of Gods word.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Zechariah: 5.4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>I will bring forth a curſe (ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes) and it ſhall enter into the houſe of the thiefe, and into the houſe of him that falſlie ſweareth by my Name; and it ſhall remaine in the midſt of his houſe, and ſhall conſume it with the timber thereof, and ſtones thereof.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Creede,</hi> for <hi>Arthur Iohnſon,</hi> Dwelling at the ſigne of the white Horſe in Pauls Church-yard. 1614.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:28"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:28"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>William Hinſon</hi> Eſquire, grace and peace, in the Prince of peace Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue once againe laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched forth from a ſafe Hauen into a turbulent and tempeſtuous ſea of Mens humours; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed my ſelfe afreſh to the carping cenſure of hateſome <hi>Criticall Loylus,</hi> and filthie <hi>Black-mouthed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> whoſe virulent tongue is no fuller of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then the venemous Viper; and the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their lippes no better then the vomit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>Aſpes:</hi> a prophane and degenerate gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation, euer readier to find two faults in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her, then to amende one in themſelues. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecauſe in my other workes I haue proclaimed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pen defiance vnto ſuch (but for modeſtie ſake without name) and meane, if they perſiſt in
<pb facs="tcp:19222:29"/> their impious and irreligious humour, the next time to labour to purge out their poyſon with a dramme of <hi>Mythredatim,</hi> and ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomize their names in print.<note place="margin">In a worke which I haue in hand; intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomie of a Chriſtian.</note> At this time I thinke them not worthie of farther ſpeech, but onely in my prayers. I confeſſe, ſilence had beene more ſecure: yet may I freely proteſt, that no conceit of mine owne gifts, nor the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the vaine applauſe of mens mouthes, but an vnfeined deſire to doe good (according to my poore talent) and that by all meanes, in the Church of God (being alſo heartned by the good acceptance of my former labours, with the well inclined, and the profite and comfort they ingeniouſlie confeſſe they haue reaped thereby) hath encouraged mee to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede herein. This (Right Worſhipfull) I preſumed to cenſecrate, and dedicate vnto you, as a pledge of my good will and thankefulneſſe, for many your kind fauours; and eſpecially (which I ſhall neuer drench in obliuion) your readineſſe in ſupporting my honeſt and iuſt cauſe: nay, Gods cauſe, againſt certaine igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,<note place="margin">W. Iohnes.</note> proud, and malicious <hi>Oppoſites,</hi> which make a ſhew of godlineſſe, but haue denied the power thereof: which ſpeake of ſanctification with vnſanctified lippes: For which (I doubt not) as alſo for your loue to religion, good to
<pb facs="tcp:19222:29"/> your countrey, protection of the oppreſſed, &amp;c. there is a reward layde vp for you in heauen, euen an immarceſſible Crowne of glorie. If this (as indeede it is not) be not anſwerable to your worth, impute it not (I beſeech you) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my will, but rather to my want of abilitie, being loth to be branded with the more then barbarous note of ingratitude, which I euer deteſted, <hi>cane peius &amp; angue,</hi> knowing the old prouerbe; <hi>Omnia dixeris ſi ingratum dixeris.</hi> Now I beſeech the God of peace to ſanctifie you, that your ſoule and bodie may be kept blameleſſe vnto the day of the Lord.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips in all duetie, WILLIAM EST.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:30"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19222:30"/>
                  <head>THE IVDGES AND IVRIES INSTRVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Ioh. 7.51</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.51.</note>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Doth our law iudge a man before it heare him and know what he hath done?</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O omitte all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of time, place and perſons: This queſtion (as our Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Logick</hi> ſay) may be reſolued into a propoſition: or (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>Rethoritians</hi> ſay) implieth a propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on with an abſurditie vpon the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e: As that, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25.</note> 
                     <hi>Shall not the Iudge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> all the world doe right?</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hall wee continue in ſinne that grace may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>und? God forbid.</hi> So that it is in effect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s if hee had ſayde; Our law doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dge any man before it heare him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>now what hee hath done. Wherein obſerue three things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19222:31"/>
                     <item>
                        <note place="margin">The diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>1. That the law muſt iudge, or the Iudge by the lawe: <hi>Doth our la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> iudge?</hi> and this requireth in the Iudge knowledge of the law, and obedience to the law.</item>
                     <item>2. What is the ſubiect of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which muſt bee iudged? a Man: which teacheth the Iudge to to iudge warilie, and without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons impartiallie.</item>
                     <item>3. The order that the law requireth in iudgement; <hi>To heare the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſpeake for himſelfe, and to know wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> he hath done.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>For the firſt, the written law, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> good ſoeuer it bee, is dead in it ſelfe like a ſword layd vp in ſcabert, or preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Oyntment ſhut vp in a boxe: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Magiſtrate therefore is added, to reuiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this dead body of the law,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 17.21.</note> as <hi>Elias</hi> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the childe being dead, by ſtretching himſelfe vpon it: By which coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the law becomes a Magiſtrate, and the Magiſtrate a law: The Magiſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lendeth a mouth to the law to ſpeake and the law teacheth him a rule to ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aright. So that hence this poynt is mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> playne; The law muſt iudge by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrates
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19222:31"/> mouth, and the Magiſtrate by the law, as the mouth by the heart. This may be gathered by the words of <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> here, when he maketh the law the Iudge; <hi>Doth our law iudge a man befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> it heare him, and know what he hath do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>?</hi> by the mouth of the Iudge, or the Iudge, according to the law. And therefore the Lord commaundeth <hi>Ioſhua to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in the law day and night,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioſhua.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>and not to let it depart from him.</hi> Which alſo is meant of the <hi>Iudiciall law;</hi> And an argument here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are <hi>Pauls</hi> words to <hi>Ananias;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 23.</note> 
                     <hi>God ſhall ſmite thee thou whited wall; for thou fitteſt to iudge me according to the law, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt mee to bee ſmitten contrarie to the law.</hi> Wherein we learne two things: 1. That the Magiſtrate is ſet in place of Iuſtice, to iudge according to the law. 2. That therefore the ſinne is great to iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the law; but to iudge contrarie to the law, deſerues to bee ſmitten of God himſelfe. Neither muſt wee thinke that this law of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> had onely this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue: for euery good law hath the ſame that the Ciuill law hath:<note place="margin">lib. <hi>40.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut de officio Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis.</note> As <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> ſheweth; <hi>lib.</hi> 40. <hi>inſtitut. intitulo de officio Iudicis:</hi> Where, in the very firſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19222:32"/> words he faith; <hi>Imprimis illud obſeruare debet Iudex ne aliter iudicet qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>legibus, &amp;c.</hi> The Iudge ought eſpecially to obſerue, that he iudge no otherwiſe then by the lawes, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And that the lawes in ſeuerall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries had the ſame authoritie, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by <hi>Eſchines</hi> Oration;<note place="margin">Echines.</note> wherein hee affirmeth, that the <hi>Athenian</hi> Magiſtrates were ſworne thereto. Whereunto it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, <hi>Themiſtocles</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> had refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, when <hi>Simonides</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Simonides.</note> the Poet reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted him to giue ſentence with him in a matter vniuſt, anſwered; <hi>Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tu bonus poeta ſi praeter muſicae modulos caneres, ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ego Iudex iuſtus ſi contra leges pronunciem:</hi> Neyther art thou a good Poet, if thou violate the rules of muſicke; neither am I an vpright Iudge, if I giue ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt law.</p>
                  <p>I ſtand not heere (though I might) to diſcuſſe that ſubtile queſtion, diſputed in the ſchooles; Whether is to bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before other, the Law or the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates? Wee are rather to giue God thankes that wee haue ſuch good lawes, and with all, good Magiſtrates to put them in execution, and to iudge accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19222:32"/> to the law: Neither yet do I ſo muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell the mouth of the Magiſtrates, as that when the law is defectiue he ſhould bee mute: but this I ſay, when the law is not defectiue, the Magiſtrate ſhould iudge according to the law. And hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth that the Iudge ought to know the law, and to obey the law. I need not (Right Honourable) to mention your knowledge in the law: but the thing that I woulde put you in minde of, is; That you would perſiſt to be as you are obedient to the law, in iudging by the law. And here would I giue you but the ſame counſell as <hi>Claudian</hi> once gaue to the Emperour Honorius.<note place="margin">Claud. in conſul. <hi>4.</hi> Hono. panegy.</note>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Vt te totius medio telluris in orbe,</l>
                     <l>Viuere cognoſcas, cunctis tua gentibus eſſe</l>
                     <l>Facta palam, &amp;c.</l>
                     <l>Nec tibi, quid liceat ſed quid feciſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebit,</l>
                     <l>Occurrat, mentem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> domet reſpectus honeſti.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that you liue in the publique view of the world,<note place="margin">An excellent counſell.</note> &amp; that your actions are open to the eyes of all men: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thinke not what lieth in your pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to doe, but what is fitte, and ſeemely
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19222:33"/> for you to doe, and let the due reſpect of honeſtie rule your minde, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe your paſſions.</p>
                  <p>All mens eies are ſixt vpon you; if you keepe the law, all will be the ſooner in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to doe the ſame. And as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth; <hi>Omnes legibus ſerui eſſe debemus vt liberi eſſe poſſimus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which you ſhall do the better, if you conſult and aduiſe often with the law, and not truſt too much to your habituall knowledge: for though you may iudge right to others, yet it may be a ſinne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſelues, and not rightly, except it bee vpon your knowledge that it is law: for none is iuſt, but he that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hee doth iuſtlie. And thus much for the firſt point; <hi>That the law muſt Iudge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing is the ſubiect <hi>of this Iudgeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t,</hi> which muſt bee iudged; <hi>A man:</hi> and this requireth in you both warineſſe, in that you muſt iudge ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a creature as Man; and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialitie, in that you muſt iudge a Man without reſpect of any ſtate or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition whatſoeuer, but onely as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; for the excellencie of man. To omit all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations that the Philoſophers gather,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19222:33"/> and onely as <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> to ſhew you but a cluſter of theſe grapes: the making of the leaſt creature in the world (in that betwixt being, and not being, there is no proportion) required as great a power as God Almightie, ſo that each creature in the world is, if not <hi>Imago,</hi> yet <hi>veſtigium dei,</hi> a print of God;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</note> yet in Gen: ſhal we finde, that of all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures God ſaid let them be, and they were: onely when he comes to make man, doth as it were (to ſignifie the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the worke he had in hand) call a counſell and ſaith: <hi>Let vs make man, not as other creatures;</hi> a darke reſemblance of vs, but in our owne likenes and ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude. So that the whole worke of the <hi>creation,</hi> is by ſome compared vnto a chaine, reaching from earth to heauen, wherein man as he lookes vp to God, is ranged in order with his fellow crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but as he lookes downe vpon the earth is Lord and chiefe of all.<note place="margin">Dyoniſius</note> But leaſt ſome ſhuld replie, that theſe priuiledges belonged onely to man in his eſtate of innocencie, but now they belong not to him, nor any ſuch excellencie, no more then the kingdom of <hi>Sicilia</hi> to <hi>Dionyſius,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19222:34"/> when he taught in the ſchoole. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: As it is loſt in one, ſo it is loſt in euery man which is ſufficient for this purpoſe; but that it is not abſolutely loſt in any,<note place="margin">Ge n:</note> God himſelfe witneſſeth, Gen: 9. <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, for in the Image of God hath he made him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat:</hi> 2.16.</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider now with what wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines you ſhould iudge man, ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent creature, euen the image of God. This reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred, would haue kept <hi>Herode</hi> from ſo haſtie murthering of ſo many harmeles infants, and the bloodie <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their more then ſauage murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the poore <hi>Indians.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Spaniards towards the Indians.</note> And ſurely I ſhould hardly beleeue it, were it not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by a <hi>Biſhop</hi> of their own, one <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomeus,</hi> how that in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſt of the weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> they were accuſtomed to ſlay the <hi>Indians</hi> to feede their dogges withall. This is ſo horrible &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to mans nature, that me thinkes it ſhould be incredible. But if they were ſo ſauage towards them that were men as well as they, but that they wanted a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, how would they (thinke you) deale with vs whom they count <hi>Heretikes,</hi> and worſe then <hi>Infidelles?</hi> But to returne to the point; The ancient
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19222:34"/> 
                     <hi>Romanes</hi> (for in the latter time they were more corrupted) ſhall riſe in iudgement againſt thoſe Magiſtrates which regard not as they ought, what they iudge.<note place="margin">Ttus <hi>9.</hi> flam.</note> 
                     <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Flam:</hi> amongſt them was put out of his office and diſgraded, for that he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a man that was before condemned, to be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged in his parlour. A mans life is not a matter to be plaied with, or ieſted at: and this is that which God would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh his people of, Deut: 17.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut:</hi> 17.</note> that their Iudges ſhould be of their owne people &amp; brethren, euen men like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and not ſtrangers, but of Gods people, inſtructed in his law, which well knewe the excellent ſubiect of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is (Man) Gods moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent creature.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal:</hi> 8.4.</note> As did king <hi>Dauid</hi> when in the deepe conſideration thereof he ſaid, <hi>What is man, ſay I, that thou art mindfull of him, and the ſonne of man, that thou viſiteſt him?</hi> Howbeit, far be it from me that I ſhould ſeeke to hinder the ſeueritie of Iuſtice: I knowe that there is no crueltie ſo bad, as that which ſomtimes masketh vnder the name of mercy: and I knowe alſo that our age rather requireth ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie then lenitie, &amp; fewer would doe euill vpon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19222:35"/> if they ſawe puniſhment duly executed vpon malefactors. But as the Iudges ought to be vpright in all cauſes, ſo chiefely in matters of blood, for feare nor fauour to winke at murther, that when ſuch a one is conuicted before them, they may ſay with the Elders of <hi>Iſrael, Our hands haue not ſhed his blood, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue our eyes ſeene it.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.</note> For if the Iudge be partiall herein, though he did no vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, yet his eyes haue ſeene it, and winked at it, and he ſaid nothing. A no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example to this purpoſe we haue, 1. Reg: 20. where God ſent this meſſage vnto the king of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe he let <hi>Benhadas</hi> goe, whom God had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to die, <hi>thy life ſhall goe for his life, and thy p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ople for his people.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 20.</note> But this is it I commend vnto your Lo: which was ſo much praiſed in <hi>Sulpicius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sulpicius</note> of whom it is ſaide, that he neuer iudged any man vnaduiſedly, nor euer tooke pleaſure in the iuſt execution of iudgement: but his teares were often ſeene to trickle from his eies when he pronounced iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of death vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any man.<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Eagles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d.</note> So when you come as Chirurgions to launce by law corrupt members, that the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19222:35"/> be preſerued, you muſt come, though with an eagles eye, and a Lyons hart, yet with a Ladies ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; iudge man as man: that is, as an excellent creature, warily: yet as a man without partialitie, boldly. In that dangerous time when <hi>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ece</hi> had almoſt loſt her libertie,<note place="margin">Adiman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus and Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</note> 
                     <hi>Animantus</hi> repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> becauſe he was too ſlacke: he anſwered, that ſuch were bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten commonly in the <hi>Olimpian</hi> games which were too forward; yea quoth <hi>Themistocles, ſed nec eos quiſe ſubdu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronat quiſquam,</hi> but none crowneth them that conuey themſelues out of the way.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adimantus</hi> noted <hi>Themistocles</hi> of raſh audacitie, and he againe accuſed the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of timerouſnes, who detracted to fight when opportunitie ſerued. I wiſhed your Lo: to make no more haſte then good ſpeede, and now I muſt beſeech you not to ſtay when you ſhould goe forward, not to ſtay iudgement though it be againſt mightie men, though it may be you may haue ſome to lay holde on the skirt of your gowne to ſtay you: not to puniſh in one, what you will ſpare in an other: A fearefull Iudge that ſtandeth in feare of the mightie, will be ſwaied by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19222:36"/> the authouritie of the mightie, and is made ſuch a ſlaue to his affections, that the leaſt thing will corrupt him. Thus ſaith the mirrour of wiſedome,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro:</hi> 28.</note> 
                     <hi>To haue reſpect of perſons is not good, for ſuch a one will tranſgreſſe for a morſell of bread.</hi> Surely there is not one point in the Iudges office whereunto the ſcripture ſpeaketh more then to this. <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> placing iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ouer <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron:</hi> 19.</note> exhorted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaying: <hi>Let the feare of God be vpon you, take heede and doe it: for there is no iniquitie with the Lord our God, neither respect of perſons, nor taking reward.</hi> This is alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by God, Leuit: 19.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leuit:</hi> 19.</note> Deut: 1.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut:</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>You ſhall haue no reſpect of perſons in iudgement, but ſhall heare the ſmall as well as the great, ye ſhall not feare the face of man.</hi> And the reaſon is added: <hi>for the iudgement is Gods.</hi> And it is the ſame that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith in this chap: ver: 23. <hi>Iudg not according to the appearance, but iudge with righteous iudgement.</hi> Neither is it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnlawfull to iudge partially, but alſo vnprofitable in the ende, for it hath euer the curſe of God, and the people purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro:</hi> 24.</note> As <hi>Salomon</hi> teacheth, ſaying; <hi>It is not good for to haue any reſpect of perſon in iudgement: for he that ſaith to the wicked,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19222:36"/> thou art righteous, him ſhall the people curſe, and the multitude ſhall abhorre him:</hi> And for the curſe of God, Eſa: 5.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſa:</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Woe be vnto him that calleth good euill, and euill good,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</note> 
                     <hi>which put darknes for light, and light for darknes, that put bitter for ſweete, and ſweete for ſower. Plutarch</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Thebans</hi> a very prudent kinde of people in <hi>Greece,</hi> were wont to painte in their temples this forme of an vpright Senate, the Iudges ſitting without eyes and hands, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it no matter if they wanted both eies and hands, if they had a tongue and eares, inferring therby, an incorrupt iudgement.</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Cur ſine ſunt manibus? capiant ne xenia,<note place="margin">Alciatus. Emble. <hi>144.</hi>
                           </note> nec ſe</l>
                        <l>Pollicitis flecti, muneribuſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſinant.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Why want they hands? to ſignifie that bribes they ſhould not take,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet with promiſes be wonne, true iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to forſake.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">S. Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ad Eugenium lib: <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> that a good Iudge ſhould feare God, and nothing but him, and looke for nothing in regard of his iudgement but from God. <hi>Ageſelaus,</hi> though otherwiſe a good Prince, yet
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19222:37"/> he had this noted in him as a great ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh to his iuſtice,<note place="margin">A great blemiſh in <hi>Ageſelaus.</hi>
                     </note> that he wrote to the Iudge in the behalfe of his friend <hi>Nicias,</hi> that if <hi>Nicias</hi> be not guiltie, <hi>dimit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> acquite him; if he be found guiltie, <hi>mihi dimitte,</hi> acquite him for my ſake: and howſoeuer it be, <hi>omnino dimitte,</hi> yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite him. <hi>Pericles</hi> was wont to ſay, that when hee put on him the perſon of a Judge,<note place="margin">Pericles.</note> he put off the perſon of a friend: ſo that this is plaine, that no reſpect of man is to be had, eſpecially in matters of right &amp; wrong. And this is the cauſe that <hi>Nichodemus</hi> raiſed vp this propoſition, from the particular, to the generall, not ſaying [this man] but [a Man] any man whatſoeuer. For as the prouerbe is, Let the Diuel haue his right. <hi>Cyrus in Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cyrus in Zenoph:</note> being made a Iudge, thought he did iuſtly, when he gaue the longeſt cloake to the talleſt man, and the ſhorter to the little man: but he was beaten for it, and taught to giue each man his owne without regard of conueniencie. I ſpeake not this as if there ſhould not be diſtinction of lawes for ſeuerall eſtates, others for Noble men, and others for common perſons, but where the law
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19222:37"/> makes no difference, there in <hi>Anacharſis</hi> ſpiders webbe, the litle flies muſt not be caught, and the great drones muſt goe through:<note place="margin">Galbas iudgment memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> Nay if Gentlemen offend their offence is worſe. Therfore <hi>Galbaes</hi> iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was moſt excellent, when he was ruler of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and had adiudged a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman to be hanged: he pleaded that he was a gentleman, and therefore ſhould haue more fauour then a common per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: you ſhall ſaith <hi>Galba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> for you ſhall not be hanged on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon gallowes, but you ſhall haue one of purpoſe made for you, higher then the other: and it ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be carued and painted too if you will. I ſtand not on the circumſtances, ſo the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be performed. And ſo with this noble patterne of Iuſtice, I ende this 2. point, which is the ſubiect of iudgement, <hi>[a Man]</hi> which teacheth the Iudge, to iudge warily, and without reſpect of perſons.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The third thing is the order to be obſerued in iudgement, which is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in theſe words: <hi>Before it h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>are him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd knowe what he hath done</hi> Where we are taught, that (firſt in generall,) enquirie &amp; knowledge muſt goe before iudgement: 2. in particular, that this enquirie muſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19222:38"/> be to knowe what the man hath done 3. How we muſt come to knowe this, by hearing him ſpeake for himſelfe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the firſt, that inquirie muſt goe before iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; God himſelfe hath put it out of all queſtion, in conuenting <hi>Adam</hi> to knowe what he had done, before he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced ſentence vpon him. Gods eyes cannot be blinded, for he beholdeth all things, yet herein he dealeth with man, as if he himſelfe were not God; to teach the Gods on earth, which ſee but in part, how they ſhould proceed in iudgement: and this he teacheth: Deut. 1.16.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut:</hi> 1.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Firſt heare, and then iudge the controuerſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your brethren.</hi> And Deut: 13. they are willed in cauſes of idolatrie, in euery Citie to make diligent enquirie whether the report be true. This being ſo, where ſhall the vnrighteous Iudge appeare, which iudgeth before the enquirie? The example of <hi>Piſo</hi> is very incommendable, who when a ſouldiour returned into the campe without his fellowe with whom he went forth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned him forthwith to death, as a murtherer of his fellowe: who comming in as he was going to execution,<note place="margin">A tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and cruell ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> the <hi>Centurion</hi> that led him, brought both backe againe to <hi>Piſo;</hi> who
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19222:38"/> being incenſed therewith, commanded all three to be put to death. He ſhall die (ſaith he to the Centurion) becauſe he is condemned: and the other for that he was the cauſe that he was condemned; and thou becauſe thou diddeſt not obey my iudgement in putting him to death. This was a cruell iudgement, but the cauſe hereof we ſee to be for want of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie before. Very memorable is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Phillip of Macedon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philip of Macedon.</note> who ſitting in iudgement to heare the cauſe of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>haetes,</hi> but being <hi>dormitabundus,</hi> drouſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t attentiue to the equitie of the lawe, gaue ſentence againſt him. But when <hi>Machaetes</hi> cried out that he would appeale from that ſentence;<note place="margin">Eraſmus.</note> The king very angrie, ſtood vp and ſaide; To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wilt thou appeale from me? He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wered, to thy ſelfe (ô King) if thou wilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wake &amp; way my cauſe aright; finding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen, vpon better conſideration, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad done him iniurie, reuoked not his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entence, but payed himſelfe the money wherin <hi>Machaetes</hi> was condemned. What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n example is this of patience, modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion and loue of Iuſtice in a Prince?</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The inquirie muſt be made what a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ath done, which is meant of open actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19222:39"/> &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſion of the lawe, for the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the hart Gods law only can take holde of, and they intrude themſelues into Gods office, which ſeeke to enquire of this: But this is it I ſay, that the lawe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to iudge of the outward action: and yet I graunt that the action is to be conſidered as it comes from the heart, for one and the ſame thing may be done by one well, and by an other ill, ſo that we muſt in the action, conſider the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with the qualitie, and therefore we enquire whether a man did take a thing away felloniouſly or not; for ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time and in ſome caſe, the intention may alter the conſideration of the action, as in caſe of defence: but this is true, <hi>ſine cauſa nemo iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> punitur, ſine culpa nemo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 The maner to know what the man hath done, is by hearing him ſpeake for himſelfe, for it is not iuſt onely to hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the plaintiffe ſpeake, but the defendan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> muſt alſo. This God taught in comming downe to ſee <hi>Gomorah</hi> before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioſhua:</hi> 7.</note> So <hi>Ioſhua</hi> could not iudge <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan</hi> before he had confeſſed the fault and this is not onely Gods lawe, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lawe of Nations,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act:</hi> 24.</note> as of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Feſtus</hi> proceeding againſt <hi>Paul</hi> ſheweth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19222:39"/> Act: 24. And of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> as <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſthenes</hi> noteth in an Oration. Where he vrgeth it, as part of the dutie of a Iudge to heare both parties:<note place="margin">Audi al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teram par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</note> and this is it which <hi>Alexander</hi> was ſo much commended for, who was wont to ſtop one eare when he heard the Plaintiffe, and being asked why he did ſo, anſwered, <hi>alteram <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram ſeruo,</hi> I keepe the other free for the Defendant. And this is the practiſe in matters of right and wrong. Wherein I would beſeech you Lo: to put in minde theſe skilfull pleaders and Lawyers, that they remember the truſt that is repoſed in them, that they doe not as many that will not ſpeake at all: and why? <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>bos in lingua.</hi> Or as the prouerbe that ſprang of <hi>Demoſthenes: Argentangina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patiuntur,</hi> they are ſicke of the <hi>ſiluer ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> For as <hi>Aul: Gellius</hi> reporteth, when he pleaded very ſharpely againſt the <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Ambaſſadours which came to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> to craue ſome aide, ſo that they were like to haue the repulſe: the matter being referred till the next day, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours went in the meane time to <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> &amp; gaue him a great ſumme of money to holde his peace, and not to pleade againſt them. The next day when
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19222:40"/> the matter was to be heard, he fained himſelfe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> that is <hi>anginum pati.</hi> to be ſicke of the ſquinancie, and therefore could not ſpeake. Then one who had ſmelled out his hypocriſie, cried out, that <hi>Demoſthenes non</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ſed</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>pati</hi> (that is) <hi>argentanginam pati</hi> that he was ſiluer-ſicke, or a right muck-worme. So as one ſaith of ſuch, <hi>peſtifera eſt cauſidico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m lingua, niſi funibus argenteis vincias</hi> the Lawyers tongue is dangerous, and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vnles thou binde it with ſiluer cords: for not onely their ſpeech, but alſo their ſilence is venall. I hope there be no ſuch peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cankers of the common-wealth, if there be any ſuch, which ſet their wit, eloquence, and conſcience, &amp; all to ſale, to boulſter out vniuſt cauſes, I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unſaile them betimes to repent, for God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath alreadie denounced woe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. <hi>Woe be vnto them that ſpeake good of euill, &amp; euill of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ood, &amp;c.</hi> And others there are which ſpeake ſo coldly,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai:</hi> 5.</note> as if it nothing concerned them, which was ſo heynous a thing among the <hi>Romanes,</hi> that they counted it no better then plaine theft, as <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaith in his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for <hi>Roſcio.</hi> To reaſon a little this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19222:40"/> point, I haue choſen thee to ſpeake for me in my cauſe: and it may be the vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of me lies in thy hands: Is it then ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or negligence, that thou doeſt not ſpeake ſo as thou ſhouldeſt? If thou pleade ignorance, then why doeſt thou deceiue an other man, by ſelling that which thou haſt not? If thou ſaieſt that thou wouldeſt learne lawe by pleading, it is all one as if a Chirurgion ſhould kill men to learne skill by practiſe: If thou be aſhamed of ignorance, &amp; pleade neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, then thou makeſt thy fault grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and deſerueſt the puniſhment of a falſe witnes; Is it then to maintaine thy eſtate, and to leaue thy poſteritie rich? Knoweſt thou not that the ſpirit of God ſaith,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro:</hi> 21.</note> 
                     <hi>The gathering of riches by a deceitfull tongue, is vanitie toſſed too &amp; fro of them that ſeeke death.</hi> Firſt toſſed like a tennis ball from one heire to an other, &amp; purchaſeth death to the gotter. And it is the iuſt iudgement of God, that they that prey vpon their inferiours, as the great fiſhes vpon the ſmall, ſhall in the end be a fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prey vnto a greater then themſelues.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Dum praedo vis eſſe minoris,</l>
                     <l>Praeda es maioris.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:19222:41"/>
                  <p>I would therefore beſeech your Lo: (as I ſaide) often to put in minde theſe Pleaders of their dutie in that behalfe: and this is the manner of iuſt proceeding in matters of right and wrong.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The Iuries charge.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro:</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.7.</note>NOw to the Iurie and witneſſes, not I, but the Lord ſpeaketh, by the mouth of good king <hi>Iehoſophat,</hi> as I ſaide before: <hi>Let the feare of the Lord be vpon you: take heede and do it, for there is no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie with the Lord our God, neither reſpect of perſons, nor receiuing of reward:</hi> for if for feare, fauour, hatred, or to gratifie ſome great man, ye giue wrong verdite, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the execrable and damnable ſinne of periurie) ye are no better before God then men of blood, and the feareful ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God muſt needs light vpon you, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming, both of roote and branch, as the Lord hath threatned, Eſa: 5.24.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſa:</hi> 5.24.</note> 
                        <hi>Therefore as the flame of fire conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſtubble, and as the chaffe is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the flame; ſo their roote ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> as rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe, and their bud ſhall riſe vp like duſt, becauſe they haue coſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ff the lawe of the Lord of hoſtes, and contemned the word of the holy
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19222:41"/> one of Iſrael</hi> the truth whereof is verified by many wofull examples before our eyes.</p>
                     <p>Saint <hi>Hierom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> expounding this place of <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>erem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>:</hi> 4.2.<note place="margin">Hier.</note> 
                        <hi>And thou ſhall ſweare the Lord liueth in truth, in iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ment and in righteouſneſſe.</hi> For the auoyding of periurie, <hi>Tres in am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nti com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>es eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere;</hi> That there ought to be three com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of an Oath, to trueth it pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that wee ſweare not falſlie; vnto righteouſnes, that wee ſweare nothing that is vniuſt, filthie, or vnhoneſt; to iudgement, that wee ſweare not vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetlie and raſhlie, that is, for euery light occaſion wee vſurpe not the moſt reuerend Name of God.</p>
                     <p>Now,<note place="margin">The horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinne of Periurie.</note> how grieuous this ſinne of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie is, it appeareth many waies; as the ſpirit of God, after a wonderfull maner ſhewed to the Prophet <hi>Zacharias</hi> in the viſion of a flying Booke.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ch</hi> 5. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 23.11.</note> And the wiſe man ſaith; <hi>A man that vſeth much ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſhall bee filled with wickednes, and the plague ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ll neuer goe from his houſe &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. The periured perſon is a ſacriligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thiefe, becauſe he aſſumeth the holy Name of God, againſt the will of God, and God forbidding it, to be a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19222:42"/> of a falſhood. A ſacriligious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in that he inuadeth holy things to build his ſinne vpon them; as the Name of God, his bodie, his wounds, &amp;c. which other ſinners doe not. Yea, the very Diuels doe tremble and feare at the reuerend Name of God, and by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation thereof, depart out of the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed: but theſe (worſe in this reſpect then the very Diuels) prophane and blaſpheme the holy Name of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all feare. O horrible impietie!</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The falſe ſwearer doth homage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Diuell, in holding vp his hands in falſe proteſtations, or touching the booke, by his falſe oath, he worſhippeth the Diuell, &amp; renounceth God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as an ancient Father ſaith; <hi>Manus tam diù manet di <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bali quouſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> paeniteat.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. The falſe ſwearer falſifieth the Seale of the high King: and therefore, as a Traytor vnto God, is to bee caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the perpetuall priſon, there to bee tormented <hi>in the Luke that burneth with fire and brimſtone for euer,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> becauſe hee vſurpeth the Name of God, which is the Seale and witneſſe of all trueth, to bee a ſeale, teſtimonie, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19222:42"/> of lyes and falſedood: And therefore the Lord calleth falſe ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, A defiling and polluting of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Name:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.12.</note> 
                        <hi>Ye ſhall not ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r by my Name falſlie, neither ſhalt thou defile the Name of thy God: I am the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. The falſe ſwearer (as much as in him lyeth) maketh GOD a partaker in his wickedneſſe, when hee bringeth him to be witneſſe and a iuſtifier of his falſhood: And therefore in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Iudgement, and in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> laſt Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Lord hath threatned to bee a ſwifte witneſſe againſt falſe ſwearers: <hi>Mala.</hi> 3.5.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
                        <hi>I will came neere to you into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I will bee a ſwifte witneſſe againſt the Southſayers, and againſt the Adulterers, and againſt falſe ſwearers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Such periured perſons (as much as in them lyeth) ſeeke to doe Chriſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iniurie then they that crucified him: For they (ſayth a Father) <hi>Intulere Chriſto malum paenae, ſed periuris (quantum in ſe eſt) Chriſtum vult inuoluere malo cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ae;</hi> For they layde vpon innocent Chriſt the puniſhment due for ſinne: but the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured perſons (as much as in them lieth)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19222:43"/> will make Chriſt guiltie of their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which is farre worſe: for hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Chriſt to be a falſe witneſſe, a liar, and a iuſtifier of an vntruth; men worſe then the very Diuell himſelfe: for though he be a lyar,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.</note> and <hi>the father of lies,</hi> and by lies ſeduceth the world, yet hee neuer approueth his lies with an Oath, making God a partaker of his malice, that he might the ſooner deceiue, as the falſe ſwearer doth.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. The falſe ſwearer excludeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from the protection of the Name of God, againſt whom hee ſinneth. It is a common ſaying; <hi>Fruſtra inuocat legis auxilium qui in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>gem committit;</hi> He doth in vaine craue aide of the law, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth againſt the law: <hi>Our helpe</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>is in the Name of the Lord:</hi> And <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.10.</note> 
                        <hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righteous runneth vnto it and are helped.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>O that by any meanes I might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all Chriſtians which tender their ſaluation; eſpecially ſuch as are called to this great and weightie buſineſſe of Pleading, or to bee of the Iurie, or Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes concerning the life, liuing, or right
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19222:43"/> of their brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O that I might (I ſay) ſo much preuaile with them, as that among ſo many houres of the day which they ſpend in idle, vaine, and futile thoughts, talke, play, or fruitleſſe exerciſes, they would imploy, if it were but one houre of the day (after the example of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine holy man) in reading, meditating, and pondering of one little Booke, but <hi>trium foliorum,</hi> of three leaues, which I will commit to your Chriſtian confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. I haue read of a certayne holy man, who at firſt had led a ſociable and diſſolute life; that chancing on a time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the companie of an honeſt and godly man (ſuch is the force of godly ſociety) hee in ſhort time ſo wrought by whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome perſwaſions with his affections, that hee vtterly renounced his former courſe of life, and gaue himſelfe to a more priuate, auſtere, moderate, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſe kind of liuing. The cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being demaunded by one of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer companions, who woulde haue drawne him (ſuch is the nature of euill companie) to his vſuall riot.<note place="margin">Note this.</note> He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; That he was as yet ſo buſied in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a little Booke, which was but a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19222:44"/> Book of three leaues, that he had no ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſo much as to thinke of any other buſineſſe. And being asked againe a long time after, whether hee had read o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer theſe three leaues: He replyed, that theſe three leaues were of three ſeuerall coloures,<note place="margin">The Booke of three leaues, Red, White, and Blacke.</note> redde, white &amp; blacke, which contayned ſo many Miſteries, that the more hee meditated thereon, the more ſweetneſſe he alwayes found, ſo that he had deuoted himſelfe to meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all the dayes of his life. In the firſt leafe, which is redde, I meditate (quoth he) on the paſſion of my Lord and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; of his pretious blood ſhed for a ranſome of my ſinnes, and the ſinnes of the whole world, without which, we had beene all the bondſlaues of Sathan, and fuell for hell fire. In the white leafe, I cheere vp my ſpirit, with the comfortable conſideration of the vnſpeakable ioyes of the heauenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, purchaſed by the pretious blood of my Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, a motiue of thankfulneſſe. In the third leafe, which is blacke, I meditate vpon the horrible and perpetuall torments of hell, prepared for the wicked and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19222:44"/> as lyars, periured perſons, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, adulterers, extortioners, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, oppreſſours, &amp;c. and all impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinners, from which the godly are freed, by the death of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>This Booke of three leaues, if wee woulde alwaies carry in our hearts, and meditate often therein, great (ſurely) would be the benefite wee ſhould make thereby, to reſtrayne our thoughts and actions within the regularitie and limits of the feare of God.</p>
                     <p>But (ô good God) what periuries are are now vſed euery where, eſpecially in buying &amp; ſelling? cuſtome hath brought it to ſuch a ſhameleſſe habite, that he is counted an Ideot in his trade, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not grace his wares which are naught, with a thouſand oathes and periuries: <hi>Merces ſuas plus periurijs quam pretijs one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Caſſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r.</note> Lading his wares more with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries then with prices.</p>
                     <p>And ſurely (not without great cauſe) God commaunded lying Witneſſes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely to bee puniſhed: for in this one ſinne, many and moſt grieuous ſinnes are included. It is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ioyned with periurie; &amp; what an horrible thing is it,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19222:45"/> that Man ſhould not be afrayd to take a falſe Oath; and call God, the God of truth, to bee a witneſſe to an vntruth? What is this elſe but a reproach that toucheth the perſon of God himſelfe? and therefore a polluting and defiling of the reuerend Name of God: as God himſelfe calleth it; <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uit.</hi> 19<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Leuit.</hi> 19.</note> What is this elſe but voluntarily to forſake God, and all the ſweete promiſes of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life and his Kingdome (all which are contayned in Gods booke on which they ſweare) and willingly to betray their ſoules into the hands of Sathan?</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Hence it followeth, that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured man is in his heart (vndoubtedly) an Infidel, and <hi>ſaith in his he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>t, there is no Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>:</hi> for if he were verilie perſwaded of the <hi>Godhead,</hi> which knoweth al things, <hi>ſearcheth the heart and reine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> and is a iuſt reuenger of all wickedneſſe; he would ſurely tremble and bee afrayde in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth to appeale to the God of truth.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. He grieuouſlie ſinneth againſt his Neighbour, by taking from him by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, his liuing, life, or good name.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. The falſe witneſſe is alſo a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, for (as much as in him lieth) he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19222:45"/> giueth his neighbour a deadly wound, when by his falſe oath he hurteth him, in body, goods, or name: therefore the falſe witnes, by the lawe of God, was to endure the ſame puniſhment which he thought to bring vpon his neighbour, <hi>an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut:</hi> 19.21.</note> life for life: as if with violent hand he had pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out his neighbours eye, or taken away his life.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. He violateth iudgement, and in the ſacred place of Iuſtice, he exerciſeth iniuſtice.</p>
                     <p>To conclude, he ſinneth againſt the common good and ſafegard of all men, and (as much as in him lyeth) ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth it. For it is certaine, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſacred adminiſtration of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ent and iuſtice, no common-wealth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>any long endure. Though God did ſuffer many ſinnes in <hi>Ahab,</hi> yet when he had by falſe witnes oppreſſed poore <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boath,</hi> the Lord brought him with all his houſe, to deſtruction and ruine. O let all Magiſtrates thinke vpon this, that they raſhly admit not whomſoeur to giue eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that they ſtraightly examine the witneſſes; leaſt they ſeeme to patronize
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19222:46"/> theſe peſtilent &amp; damnable men. Thinke alſo carefully vpon this, you that ſhall be at any time produced for witneſſes, that you neither diſſemble the truth, nor wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly peruert, nor omit it, and ſo ſinne againſt God and man, and deſtroy your owne ſoules. And thus I conclude, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching the God of mercies to powre downe the riches of his grace and mercy into our hearts, that we may truly ſerue him, and haue his feare euer before our eyes, that we fall not into the horrible ſinne of periurie, which hath alwaies Gods curſe, and terrible plagues purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10.11.</note> Vnto the God of all grace, who hath called vs vnto his eternall glory by Chriſt Ieſus, be glory and dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19222:46"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
